[进度: 第 27 行]
神秘博士
别再浪费时间讨论"好人"的定义了
"Waste NO MORE time arguing about what a good man should be."
去行动吧
"Be one."
马可·奥勒留
Marcus Aurelius.
你跑过来的?
Have you been running?
你还好吗?
Are you OK?
办公室有电话找你
There was a call for you, at the office.
你的医生打来的
From your doctor.
他留地址了吗
Did he leave an address?
有风
Draught!
先去古美索不达米亚玩一周
Fancy a week in Ancient Mesopotamia…
再到未来火星玩一圈如何
followed by future Mars?
那儿有鸡尾酒吗
Will there be cocktails?
卫星上有
On the moon.
那就去卫星
The moon'll do!
新工作怎么样
How's the new job?
教了什么好玩的
Teach anything good?
没有 学到什么了吗
No. Learn anything?
一点儿没有
Not a thing.
警报 检测到外部干扰
什么情况
What's happening?
我们起飞了
Whoa, whoa. We're taking off.
但是引擎都没启动
But the engines aren't going!
风车11号呼叫灰犬队长
'Windmill 11 to Greyhound Leader.'
蓝鹰已升空 准备好接收
'Blue Eagle is airborne. Ready to receive.'
我们正在赶来
'We're on our way.'
UNIT总部
伦敦塔
你好 这是凯特·斯图尔特的手机
Hello, Kate Stewart's phone?
好的 等一下
Oh, hold on.
借过 不好意思
Excuse me… sorry!
长官 长官
Ma'am! Ma'am!
渡鸦好像行动有点迟缓
The ravens are looking a bit sluggish.
告诉马尔科姆它们该换电池了
Tell Malcolm they need new batteries.
是他
It's him!
抱歉 是您的私人手机 但是
Sorry, it's your personal phone, but, well,
我听出了这铃声
I recognised the ringtone.
是他对吧
It's him, isn't it?
呼吸器
Inhaler.
博士你好 我们在野外发现了塔迪斯
Doctor, hello. We found the TARDIS in a field.
我正将它运来 -搞什么
- 'I'm having it brought in.' - No kidding!
你在哪儿
'Where are you?'
天哪
Oh, my God!
博士 我很抱歉
'Oh, Doctor, I'm so sorry,
我们不知道你在里面
we had no idea you were still in there.'
快来
Come on.
收到 新航向207 改变航线
'Roger. New heading - 207. Changing course.'
博士 -克拉拉
- Doctor?! - Clara!
博士 能听到我说话吗
Doctor, can you hear me?
貌似他听不到 -下次
- 'I don't think he can hear me.' - Next time,
先敲敲门会死吗
would it kill you to knock?
我直接带你去现场
I'm having you taken directly to the scene.
博士 喂 你还好吗
'Doctor, hello, are you OK?'
我一时半会讲不了电话了
I'm just going to pop you on hold.
博士 -博士
- 'Doctor?' - Ah! Doctor!
立正
Atten…tion!
我为什么要敬礼
Why am I saluting?
博士 作为首席科学事务官
Doctor, as Chief Scientific Officer,
请允许我代表UNIT向你致以歉意…
may I extend the official apologies of UNIT…?
凯特·莱斯布里奇-斯图尔特 给你个忠告
Kate Lethbridge-Stewart, a word to the wise.
你父亲应该告诉过你
As I'm sure your father would've told you,
我不喜欢被人拎起来
I don't like being picked up.
Be picked up：被人勾搭
他大概理解成另一个意思了
That probably sounded better in his head.
我这么做都是遵照女王的命令
I'm acting on instructions direct from the throne.
伊丽莎白一世女王陛下的密令
Sealed orders from Her Majesty, Queen Elizabeth the First.
女王? 不好意思 是伊丽莎白一世吗
The Queen? The First? Sorry, Elizabeth the First?
信物在里面
Her credentials are inside.
不 那里面
No. Inside…
围巾不错
Nice scarf.
这次怎么瞒过去
What's our cover story for this?
说是达伦·布朗的魔术 -又来
- Um, Derren Brown. - Again?
我们给他送过花了
Oh, we've sent him flowers.
博士之日
立正
Atten… tion!
注意 画廊周边完全戒严
Right, I want a secure perimeter around the gallery.
你认识她吗 伊丽莎白一世
Did you know her? Elizabeth the First?
联合情报特派组 -什么
- Unified Intelligence Task Force. - Sorry?
UNIT 他们研究外星人 各种外星人
This lot. UNIT. They investigate alien stuff, anything alien.
比如你吗 -我为他们工作
- What, like you? - I work for them.
你还有工作 -我怎么不能有工作了
- You have a job?! - Why shouldn't I have a job?
我工作可出色了
I'd be brilliant at having a job.
你才没有工作 -我有
- You don't have a job! - I do.
这就是我的工作 我现在就在干活
This is my job, i'm doing it now.
你从来没有工作 -我有 有的
- You never have a job. - I do! I do.
伊丽莎白的信物 博士
Elizabeth's credentials, Doctor.
但是
But…
这不可能啊
but that's not possible.
NO MORE.
这是画名 -我知道
- That's the title. - I know the title!
这画也叫 GALLIFREY之陨落
Also known as Gallifrey Falls.
这画不该在这里的
This painting doesn't belong here -
不该在此时此地 -显然不该
- not in this time or place. - Obviously.
这是Arcadia的沦陷
It's the fall of Arcadia,
GALLIFREY第二大城市
Gallifrey's second city.
怎么会这样 怎么可能
But how is it doing that? How is that possible?
这是幅油画
It's an oil painting…
是三维的
in 3D.
时间领主的艺术
Time Lord art.
里面比外面大 将一幕实时情景
Bigger on the inside. A slice of real time…
冻结
frozen.
伊丽莎白说了藏画地点 以及这画的意义
Elizabeth told us where to find it… and its significance.
你还好吗
You OK?
他在那里
He was there.
他是谁 -我
- Who was? - Me.
另一个我
The other me.
我绝口不提的那个我
The one I don't talk about.
我不明白
I don't understand.
我有过很多张面孔 很多次生命
I've had many faces, many lives.
但是没有全部承认
I don't admit to all of them.
有一世我尽力想要忘记
There's one life I've tried very hard to forget.
不再
NO MORE.
他是参加时间大战的博士
He was the Doctor who fought in the Time War,
就在那天他做出了那件事 我做出了那件事
and that was the day he did it - the day I did it.
那天他毁灭了一切
The day he killed them all.
时间大战的终结之日
The last day of the Time War.
终结我族和戴立克之间所有战争的那一场大战
The war to end all wars between my people and the Daleks.
在那场战役中 有一个人的双手所沾染的血
And in that battle, there was a man with more blood on his hands
比任何人都多
than any other.
这个人犯下的罪孽足以让全宇宙为之静寂
A man who would commit a crime that would silence the universe,
而那个人…就是我
and that man…was me.
时间大战终结之日
消灭
Exterminate!
通报最高议会 最优先级别
Message for the High Council, Priority Omega.
Arcadia沦陷 重复 Arcadia沦陷
Arcadia has fallen. I repeat, Arcadia has fallen.
士兵
Soldier…
我得用一下你的枪
I'm going to need your gun.
消灭
Exterminate!
求求你们 求求你们别这样
Please! Please, just don't!
警报 警报
Alert! Alert!
侦察到博士
The Doctor is detected!
博士被包围了
The Doctor is surrounded!
通知最高司令部 我们包围了博士
Inform High Command, we have the Doctor!
寻找 定位 消灭
Seek, locate, destroy!
博士被包围了
The Doctor is surrounded…
寻找 定位 消灭 寻找
Seek, locate, destroy! Seek…
博士…
The…Doctor…
逃脱了
is…escaping.
这几个字是什么意思
What…are…these…words?
解释
Explain!
最高议会正召开紧急会议
The High Council is in emergency session
他们自有计划 -最高议会都去死吧
- they have plans of their own. - To hell with the High Council
军事会议室
他们的计划失败了
their plans have already failed.
GALLIFREY依然在遭受攻击
Gallifrey's still in the line of fire.
这么说他当时在场
So he was there, then?
他留了条信息 是写给戴立克的警告
He left a message, a written warning for the Daleks.
他是个傻子
He's a fool.
不 他是个疯子
No. He's a madman.
如您所见 阁下
As you can see, sir,
包围本星球的所有戴立克舰队
all Dalek fleets surrounding the planet,
都集中火力攻击首都 但天壕依然坚固
now converging on the capital, but the Sky Trenches are holding.
他接下来去了哪儿
Where did he go next?
重要吗 这是他们最猛烈的进攻 阁下
What does it matter? This is their biggest ever attack, sir -
他们把所有手段都用上了 -阁下
- they're throwing everything at us… - Sir,
时间密室遭到破坏
we have a security breach to the Time Vaults.
是终极军械库
The Omega Arsenal,
保管所有禁用武器之处
where all the forbidden weapons are locked away.
已经不是禁用武器了
They're not forbidden any more.
全部都用来抵挡戴立克了
we've used them all against the Daleks.
不
No.
不是全部
No, we haven't.
时瞬矩不见了
The Moment is gone.
我不明白 时瞬矩是什么 我从没听说过
I don't understand. What is the Moment? I've never heard of it.
星系吞噬者
The galaxy eater.
GALLIFREY先人的终极发明
The final work of the ancients of Gallifrey,
无比强大的武器 其操作系统自有感知
a weapon so powerful, the operating system became sentient.
据传说
According to legend…
它产生出了意识
it developed a conscience.
我们从没用过吗
And we've never used it?
当一种能造成终极毁灭的武器
How do you use a weapon of ultimate mass destruction
本身能评判其使用者 你如何使用它
when it can stand in judgment on you?
只有一个人会尝试
There is only one man who would even try.
GALLIFREY的时间领主 SKARO的戴立克
Time Lords of Gallifrey, Daleks of Skaro…
我正式通知你们
..I serve notice on you all.
我袖手旁观太久了 再也不会了
Too long I have stayed my hand. NO MORE.
今天 你们让我别无选择
Today, you leave me no choice.
今天 战争将结束
Today, this war will end.
NO MORE.
怎么
How…
怎么用呢
..How do you work?
为什么总是没有个大红按钮呢
Why is there never a big red button?
喂
Hello?
有人吗
Is somebody there?
什么也没有
It's nothing.
只有一匹狼
It's just a wolf.
别坐那上面 -为什么
- Don't sit on that! - Why not?
因为那不是椅子
Because it's not a chair -
是全宇宙最危险的武器
it's the most dangerous weapon in the universe.
全宇宙最危险的武器也能当椅子啊
Why can't it be both?
你为什么停在那么远的地方
Why did you park so far away?
你不想让她看见吗
Didn't you want her to see it?
让谁看见
Want who to see?
塔迪斯啊
The TAR…DIS.
你长途跋涉
You walked for miles.
走啊走 走了这么远
And miles and miles and miles and miles.
我在思考 -我听见了
- I was thinking! - I heard you.
你听见我了
You heard me?
"NO…MORE."
"NO MORE."
'NO MORE.'
- "NO MORE." - NO MORE.
NO MORE! -住嘴
- "NO MORE!" - Stop it!
"NO MORE!"
NO MORE -你是谁
- "NO MORE." - Who are you?
启动了 离这儿远点
It's activating. Get out of here!
怎么了
What's wrong?
操作界面好热[Hot:性感]
The interface is hot.
我尽力而为
Well, I do my best.
动力源在里面
There's a power source inside…
你就是操作界面
You're the Interface?
他们肯定告诉过你时瞬矩有意识
They must have told you the Moment had a conscience.
你好
Hello!
瞧瞧你
Oh, look at you.
困在姑娘和盒子之间
Stuck between a girl and a box.
你这一生都是如此吧 博士
Story of your life, eh, Doctor?
你认识我
You know me?
我听过你
I hear you.
你们全在你那老脑袋里吵嚷不停
All of you, jangling around in that dusty old head of yours.
我特意为你选的这副模样
I chose this face and form especially for you.
这来自你的过去
It's from your past.
或者是未来 我总是搞不清楚
Or possibly your future - I always get those two mixed up.
我没有未来
I don't have a future.
我想我的名字是
I think I'm called…
罗斯·泰勒
Rose Tyler.
不对 是 不对 抱歉
No, yes, no, sorry.
不不 这种形态下 我叫
No, no, in this form, I'm called…
恶狼
..Bad Wolf.
你怕大恶狼吗 博士
Are you afraid of the big bad wolf, Doctor?
别管我叫博士 -那是你脑中的名字
- Stop calling me Doctor. - That's the name in your head.
本不该如此
It shouldn't be.
我已经战斗了太久
I've been fighting this war for a very long time -
失去了当博士的资格
I've lost the right to be the Doctor.
那你将拯救我们所有人
Then you're the one to save us all.
是的
Yes.
如果我哪天发展出自负的一面 功劳归你
If I ever develop an ego, you've got the job.
如果你进过我的脑袋里
If you have been inside my head…
那你就知道我所目睹的一切
..then you know what I've seen.
苦痛折磨
The suffering.
时空的每一处每一刻都在燃烧
Every moment in time and space is burning.
必须结束了
It must end.
我打算用我所知的唯一方法结束战争
And I intend to end it the only way I can.
你要通过我 杀死所有人来结束战争
And you're going to use me to end it by killing them all,
戴立克和时间领主都不放过
Daleks and Time Lords alike.
我可以 但你要承担后果
I could, but there will be consequences for you.
我无意生还
I have no desire to survive this.
那就是对你的惩罚
Then that's your punishment.
如果你这么做
If you do this - if you
如果你杀了所有人 那后果就是
kill them all - then that's the consequence.
你会活下去
You…live.
GALLIFREY
你要炸掉它
you're going to burn it…
还有戴立克 以及所有的孩子
and all those Daleks with it but all those children too.
现在GALLIFREY有多少孩子
How many children on Gallifrey right now?
我不知道
I don't know.
有一天你会数清
One day you will count them.
某个可怕的夜晚
One terrible night.
想知道这把你变成了什么样子吗
Do you want to see what that will turn you into?
你就一点儿也不好奇
Come on! Aren't you curious?
我正打开一个通向未来的窗口
I'm opening windows on your future.
一团穿越时空的时间混沌
A tangle in time through the days to come,
让你窥见今日之因与明日之果
to the man today will make of you.
这可不在计划内
OK, I wasn't expecting that.
但时间大战已经结束了
But the Time War's over.
为什么你要带我们来看这幅画
Why have you brought us here to look at a painting?
这幅画只是伊丽莎白的信物
The painting only serves as Elizabeth's credentials,
证明这封信的确出自她之手
proof that the letter is from her.
这不是请你来的原因
It's not why you're here.
我的最爱 我希望GALLIFREY之陨落
'My dearest love, I hope the painting known as Gallifrey Falls
可以向你证明
'will serve as proof that
此信出自你的伊丽莎白之手
it is your Elizabeth who writes to you now.
愿你还记得你曾发誓
'You will recall that you pledged yourself
要为我国之安危身先士卒
'to the safety of my kingdom.
我因此任命你
'In this capacity, I have appointed you as curator
为秘密画廊的馆长
'of the Under Gallery where
那里封锁着我英格兰的致命威胁
deadly danger to England is locked away.
高墙之内若有骚乱发生
'Should any disturbance occur within its walls,
我希望你能应召而至 祝平安 夫君
'it is my wish that you be summoned. God speed, gentle husband.'
怎么回事
What happened?
你看了就知道
Easier to show you.
麦基洛普
McGillop.
这不可能 我刚刚…
But that's not possible. I was just…
明白了 先生 但为什么要拿到那里去
Understood, sir. But…why would I take it there?
伊丽莎白一世 你认得她是吧
Elizabeth the First? You knew her, then?
老相识
A long time ago.
英格兰 1562年
出发
Allons-y!
所以我早说过了 陛下
There you go, Your Majesty, what did I tell you?
里面比外面大
Bigger on the inside!
门还是一样小 你差点把我的头夹断了
The door isn't - you nearly took my head off.
通常我才是砍别人头的那个
It's normally me who does that.
告诉我 博士
Tell me, Doctor, why I'm
我为何要在你身上浪费时间 我还有仗要打
wasting my time on you. I have wars to plan.
你还有野餐要吃
You have a picnic to eat.
你可以帮我
You could help me.
这个嘛
Well…
我的确在帮你解决食物
I'm helping you eat the picnic.
但你的胃口要用战争来满足
But you have a stomach for war.
这张脸见过硝烟战火
This face has seen conflict -
显而易见
it's clear as day.
我见过的硝烟战火你可无法想象
Oh, I've seen conflict like you wouldn't believe.
却不是用这张脸
But it wasn't this face.
不过别管这些了 陛下 快起来
But never mind that, Your Majesty - up on your feet! Up, up!
你好大胆子
How dare you?!
我可是英格兰女王
I'm the Queen of England!
我不是英格兰人
I'm not English.
伊丽莎白
Elizabeth,
你愿意嫁给我吗
will you marry me?
亲爱的 我当然愿意
Oh, my dear, sweet love. Of course I will!
上当了 -亲爱的 怎么了
- Ah! Gotcha! - My love?
第一 真正的伊丽莎白
One! The real Elizabeth
不可能接受我的求婚
would never have accepted my marriage proposal.
第二 真正的伊丽莎白
Two! The real Elizabeth would notice
会注意到我刚才随口提到有另外一张脸
when I just casually mention having a different face.
当然真正的伊丽莎白
But then the real Elizabeth
不是外太空来的会变形的外星人
isn't an alien shape-shifting from outer space!
而且
And…
叮
Ding!
那是什么
What's that?
是一个会叮的装置
It's a machine that goes…ding!
我自己做的
Made it myself.
它遇到变形基因就会亮灯
It lights up in the presence of shape-shifter DNA. Ooh.
还能在二十英尺开外微波加热冷冻食物
Also it can microwave frozen dinners from up to 20 feet
下载未来的漫画
and download comics from the future.
功能太多 -亲爱的 我不明白
- I never know when to stop. - My love, I do not understand.
我不是你亲爱的 而且你明白得很
I'm not your love. And yes, you do!
你是一个扎贡人
You're a Zygon.
扎贡人
A Zygon?
好了 别装了 扎贡人 没错
Oh, stop it, it's over! A Zygon, yes.
又大又红的橡胶怪 全身遍布吸盘
A big red rubbery thing, covered in suckers.
吻技居然很出色
Surprisingly good kisser.
真正的英格兰女王怎么可能跟人分享王权
Think the real Queen of England would just decide
就算对方是个西装合身
to share the throne with
举止老派的英俊男子
any old handsome bloke in a tight suit…
不光是发型风流潇洒
just cos he's got amazing hair
胯下还有一匹白马
and a nice horse?
是那匹马
It was the horse!
我就要当国王了
I'm going to be King!
快跑 -怎么回事
- Run - !What's happening?
我们被一个伪装成我的马的
We're being attacked by a shape-shifting alien from outer space,
外太空变形外星人攻击 -所以呢
- formerly disguised as my horse. - What does that mean?
所以 我们需要再找一匹马
It means… we're going to need a new horse.
那东西去哪里了
Where's it going?
你跑 我断后 你的子民需要你
I'll hold it off, you run. Your people need you.
我要你活着参加我们的婚礼
And I need you alive for our wedding day.
博士啊博士 干得好
Oh, good work, Doctor, nice one!
童贞女王 历史书骗人
The Virgin Queen? So much for history!
快出来
Come on!
我知道你在那里
Know you're there!
非常聪明
Oh, very clever.
有什么阴谋都别想得逞
Whatever you've got planned, forget it.
我是博士
I'm the Doctor.
我904岁了
I'm 904 years old.
我来自KASTERBOROUS星群的GALLIFREY星
I'm from the planet Gallifrey in the constellation of Kasterborous.
我是暴风降临 黑暗使者
I am the oncoming storm, the bringer of darkness,
而你…
and you are
只是一只普通的小兔子 对不对
basically just a rabbit, aren't you?
好吧 继续吃草 就是随便
OK, carry on - just a…general…
警告一下
warning.
博士
Doctor!
伊丽莎白
Elizabeth!
那东西到底是什么
That thing…explain what it is!
它想要什么
What does it want of us?
这也是我想知道的 大概是你的星球
That's what I'm trying to find out. Probably just your planet.
博士
Doctor?
离她远点 博士 那怪物可不是我
Step away from her, Doctor. That's not me, that's the creature.
这怎么可能 她是我
How is that possible? She's me.
博士 她是我
Doctor, she's me!
我 当然是我
I am, indeed, me.
这样的赞美你不配拥有
A compliment that cannot be extended to yourself.
不可思议
Extraordinary!
这怪物变得和我一模一样
The creature has captured my exact likeness -
真是奇了
this is exceptional.
奇了 女王应当斥其无礼才对
Exceptional? A Queen would call it impertinent.
女王应当感觉到有必要
A Queen would feel compelled to admire
观赏砍头的场面
the skill of the execution -
然后就安排砍头
before arranging one.
不管用了
Ah! It's not working!
可以推断出这种生物学习得很快
One might surmise the creature would learn quickly
使得自己不能被轻易识别
to protect itself from any simple means of detection.
显然你比我更了解这种生物
Clearly you understand the creature better than I.
当然这方面你有优势
But then you have the advantage.
你们两个退后 快
Back, both of you, now!
这是时间裂缝 现实世界的裂口
That's a time fissure, a tear in the fabric of reality.
什么都有可能发生
Anything could happen!
比如
For instance…
一顶毡帽
a fez.
这边
This way.
欢迎来到秘密画廊
Welcome to the Under Gallery.
所有伊丽莎白一世认定过于危险
This is where Elizabeth the First kept all art
不适合大众欣赏的艺术品都保存于此
deemed too dangerous for public consumption.
石屑
Stone dust.
重要吗
Is it important?
一千二百年来我就没踩过不重要的东西
In 1,200 years, I've never stepped in anything that wasn't.
喂 你 搞科研的吗
Oi, you! Are you sciencey?
这个嘛 是的
Oh, erm. Well, erm…yes.
有名字不 -是
- Got a name? - Yes.
很好 我老想认识个名叫"是"的人
Good, I've always wanted to meet someone called Yes.
现在 去分析一下这些石屑
Now, I want this stone dust analysed.
然后给我一式三份的报告
And I want a report in triplicate,
里面要有很多图啊表啊复杂的计算什么的
with lots of graphs and diagrams and complicated sums,
明天一早放在我桌子上
on my desk, tomorrow morning,
尽快 立刻 大笑
ASAP, pronto, LOL.
看到没 工作
See? Job.
我有桌子吗 -没有
- Do I have a desk? - No.
我还要一张桌子
And I want a desk!
组织一个团队 分析石屑的成分
Get a team, analyse the stone dust.
呼吸器
Inhaler!
你哪天可以目不斜视地走过一顶土耳其毡帽
Someday, you could just walk past a fez.
不可能
Never going to happen.
根据您的指示 一切保持原样
As you instructed, nothing has been touched.
这是我们请你来的原因
This is why we called you in.
又是三维的
3D again.
有意思 -碎玻璃有意思吗
- Interesting. - The broken glass?
不是
No…
有意思的是碎裂的方向
where it's broken from.
看碎片的形状
Look at the shatter pattern.
这些画的玻璃是从里面打破的
The glass on all these paintings has been broken from the inside.
你可以看到 这些画都是风景画
As you can see, all the paintings are landscapes
没有任何人物 -所以呢
- no figures of any kind. - So?
原本是有人物的
There used to be.
有东西从画里跑出来了
Something's got out of the paintings?
很多东西跑出来了
Lots of somethings.
危险的东西
Dangerous.
这里已经彻底搜查过了
This whole place has been searched.
没有多余的东西 也没有东西遗失
There's nothing here that shouldn't be, and nothing's got out.
不 现在别来
Oh, no! Not now!
博士 这是什么
Doctor, what is it?
现在别来 我忙着呢
No, not now - I'm busy!
跟画有关系吗
Is it to do with the paintings?
没有 这是另一回事 我记得这个
No, no. This is different. I remember this.
差不多还记得
Almost remember…
当然了
Oh, of course!
我要进去了
This is where I come in.
Geronimo-o…
博士 -等一下
- Doctor! - Wait.
这是谁
Who is this man?
我也想知道
That's just what I was wondering.
真是骨感
Oh, that is skinny.
货真价实的骨感
That is proper skinny.
我还没从这个角度看过
I've never seen it from the outside.
简直跟特效一样 竹竿人
It's like a special effect. Oi! Ha! Matchstick man!
你不会是…
You're not…
修正效用吧 -修正什么
- Compensating? - For what?
重生啊 跟抽奖一样
Regeneration - it's a lottery.
他好酷 多酷啊
Oh, he's cool. Isn't he cool?
我是博士 我超级酷
"I'm the Doctor and I'm all cool
糟糕 我还穿沙滩鞋
oops, I'm wearing sandshoes!"
你在这里干吗 我很忙
What are you doing here? I'm busy.
忙 我懂了 忙就是这种状况吗
Oh, busy? I see, is that what we're calling it, eh? Eh?
你们好 女士们 -别来这套
- Hello, ladies. - Don't start.
听着 你这次重生
Listen, what you get up to
私下干什么是你自己的事
in the privacy of your own regeneration is your business.
她们中有一个是扎贡人
One of them is a Zygon.
我不会多想的
I'm not judging you.
好可爱
Oh, lovely!
陛下们 是时候跑了
Your Majesties…probably a good time to run.
那个怪物怎么办
But what about the creature?
伊丽莎白 真的那个
Elizabeth, whichever one of you is the real one,
掉头 朝怪物相反的方向跑
turn and run in the opposite direction to the other one.
没问题 我的爱人
Of course, my love!
活下去 我的爱人
Stay alive, my love.
我跟你还没完
I am not done with you yet.
谢谢 很好
Thanks. Lovely.
我明白 为了我活下去 亲爱的
I understand. Live for me, my darling.
我们会再次相聚的
We shall be together again.
多好啊
Well, won't that be nice?
那里面有一个是扎贡人 -是啊
- One of those was a Zygon. - Yeah.
又大又红的橡胶怪 浑身是吸盘 -是
- Big red rubbery thing. Covered in suckers. - Yeah.
舌头上有毒囊
Venom sacs in the tongue.
我明白你的意思 多谢 -很好
- Yeah, I'm getting the point, thanks. - Nice.
博士 是你吗
Doctor? Is that you?
你好 克拉拉 能听见吗
Ah! Hello, Clara! Can you hear me?
可以 是我 我们能听见 你在哪儿
Yeah, it's me, we can hear you. Where are you?
我们在哪儿 -英格兰 1562年
- Where are we? - England…1562.
你在跟谁说话
Who are you talking to?
我自己
Myself.
你能回来吗
Can you come back through?
物理性通道可能不能双向通行
Physical passage may not be possible in both directions.
对了
It's… Ah!
等一下 土耳其毡帽来了
Hang on! Fez incoming!
没来
Nothing here.
那它跑哪儿去了
So where did it go?
他在跟谁说话 -他说是他自己
- Who's he talking to? - He said - himself.
保持通话 马尔科姆
Keep him talking. Malcolm?
马尔科姆 帮我找一份
Malcolm, I need you to send me
我父亲的档案 档案名 克罗默
one of my father's incident files - codenamed Cromer.
属于七零或八零年代 要看纪年规则
'70s or '80s, depending on the dating protocol.
你曾经是我
OK, you used to be me,
你经历过这些 接下来发生了什么
you've done all this before - what happens next?
我忘了
I don't remember.
这你怎么能忘
How can you forget this?!
等一下 这又不是我的错
Hey, hang on, it's not MY fault.
显然你注意力不够集中
You're obviously not paying enough attention.
反转极性
Reverse the polarity!
没用 -我们两个都在反转
- It's not working. - We're both reversing the polarity!
我知道 -我们有俩人
- Yes, I know that. - There's two of us
我反转一次 你又反转回去了
I'm reversing it, and you're reversing it back again!
极性表示很困扰
We're confusing the polarity.
有人丢了一顶土耳其毡帽吗
Anyone lose a fez?
你
You.
你怎么会在这儿
How can you be here?
更重要的是 你为什么会在这儿
More to the point, WHY are you here?
下午好
Good afternoon.
我在找博士
I'm…looking for the Doctor.
那你是来对地方了
Well…you've certainly come to the right place.
很好 好极了
Good! Right!
你们俩小子是什么人
Well, who are you boys?
当然 你们是他的同伴
Oh, of course! Are you his companions?
他的同伴
His companions?
他们找的人越来越年轻
They get younger all the time!
如果你们能把博士的大致方位指给我
Well, if you could point me in the general direction of the Doctor…
真的
Really?
对
Yeah.
真的 -你们是我 两个都是
- Really. - You're me? Both of you?
对 -那家伙也是
- Yep. - Even that one?
是的
Yes!
你们是未来的我
You're my future selves.
没错 -没错
- Yes! - Yes!
这是我的中年危机吗
Am I having a mid-life crisis?
你们为什么这样拿音速起子指着我
Why are you pointing your screwdrivers like that?
它们是科学仪器 不是玩具水枪
They're scientific instruments, not water pistols.
你们跟见了鬼一样
Look like you've seen a ghost!
不过 这时髦的造型和沙哑的声音蛮有味
Still…loving the posh, gravelly thing.
挺有说服力的
It's very convincing.
《豪言壮语》迪克·范·戴克
Brave words, Dick Van Dyke.
包围他们
Encircle them!
你们中谁是博士
Which of you is the Doctor?
英格兰女王着了魔
The Queen of England is bewitched.
我要取下博士的首级
I would have the Doctor's head.
这可真是你们的幸运日了
Well, this has all the makings of your lucky day.
我觉得现在有三个博士了
I think there's three of them now.
之前有过先例
'There's a precedent for that.'
那是什么
What is that?
又指来指去的 它们是起子
Oh, the pointing again. They're screwdrivers!
你们打算干什么 组装一个柜子阻止他们吗
What are you going to do, assemble a cabinet at them?
那 那是什么巫术
That thing…what witchcraft is it?
没错
Ah, yes!
既然你提起了 它是巫术 对对对
Now that you mention it, that is witchcraft, yes, yes, yes.
巫婆的巫术 你好 里面有人吗
Witchy-witchcraft. Hello? Hello in there?
抱歉 有人吗
Excuse me. Hello!
我是在和邪恶的井中女巫说话吗
Am I talking to the wicked witch of the well?
他在说你
He means you.
为什么我是女巫
Why am I the witch?
克拉拉 -你好
- 'Clara?' - Hello?
克拉拉 你好
Clara, hi, hello.
你好 你能否告诉这些聒噪的凡人
Hello. Would you mind telling these prattling mortals
让他们走开吗
to get themselves begone?
按他说的做
What…he said.
带点感情色彩
Yes, tiny bit more colour.
好吧
Right.
聒噪的凡人快退下
Prattling mortals, off you pop,
不然把你们变青蛙
or I'll turn you all into frogs.
没错 变青蛙 你们都听见了
Oh, frogs, nice. You heard her.
博士 发生什么了
Doctor, what's going on?
这是…颠颠倒倒的情况
It's a…timey-wimey thing.
颠什么...什么颠颠倒倒?
Timey…what? Timey-wimey?
也不知道他从哪儿学来的
I've no idea where he picks that stuff up.
女王陛下
The Queen!
你们竟然不下跪 真是胆大包天
You don't seem to be kneeling. How tremendously brave of you.
你是哪一个 另一个怎么了
Which one are you? What happened to the other one?
她身体不适
Indisposed.
女王万岁 -女王万岁
- Long live the Queen! - Long live the Queen!
逮捕这些人 把他们带到伦敦塔
Arrest these men. Take them to the Tower.
那不是英格兰女王 她是个外星复制品
That is not the Queen of England, that's an alien duplicate!
你们可以相信他的话
And you can take it from him,
他仔细检查过了 -闭嘴
- cos he's really checked. - Oh, shut up!
舌头上的毒囊
Venom sacs in the tongue.
说真的 闭嘴
Seriously, stop it!
不 等一下 伦敦塔 你说伦敦塔吗
No, hang on, the Tower! Did you say the Tower?
是的 太好了 就喜欢伦敦塔
Ah, yes, brilliant, love the Tower.
早餐请八点送来
Breakfast at eight, please.
有无线网吗
Will there be Wi-Fi?
你能别一边说话一边拍手吗
Are you capable of speaking without flapping your hands about?
可以 不行
Yes! No!
我要求立刻被监禁在伦敦塔
I demand to be incarcerated in the Tower immediately
和我的同谋 沙滩鞋以及老爷爷一起
with my co-conspirators, Sandshoes and Grandad!
老爷爷
Grandad?
那不是沙滩鞋
They're not sandshoes.
那就是
Yes, they are!
安静 可别小看了伦敦塔
Silence! The tower is not to be taken lightly.
没几个人能重见天日
'Very few emerge again.'
天哪 他真是聪明 走吧
Dear God, that man's clever. Come on!
我们去哪儿
Where are we going?
我的办公室 又被称作伦敦塔
My office. Otherwise known as the Tower of London.
你们 进去
Oi, you lot, get in there!
我们三个在一间牢房
Three of us in one cell -
如果不尽快逃出去 肯定会有怪事发生的
that's going to cause some nasty anomalies if we don't get out soon.
你在干什么
What are you doing?
帮我们逃出去
Getting us out!
音速起子对那门没用 太原始了
The sonic won't work on that - it's too primitive.
我们能不能要求换个高级点的门
Shall we ask for a better quality of door
这样我们就能逃出去了
so we can escape
好了 现在英格兰女王是个扎贡人
OK, so the Queen of England is now a Zygon,
但先别管那个 为什么我们会碰到一起
but never mind that, why are we all together?
为什么我们都在这里
Why are we all here?
我和…大下巴 我们完全不知情
Well, me and…Chinny, we were surprised.
但你是主动来找我们的
But you came looking for us -
你知道这会发生 谁告诉你的
you knew it was going to happen. Who told you?
喂 大下巴
Oi! "Chinny"?
是啊 你下巴确实很突出
Yeah, you do have a chin.
大理石 花岗岩 很多不同的石头
Marble, granite… A lot of different stone,
但都不是大楼的建筑材料
but none of it from the fabric of the building.
就像有人打碎了许多古老的雕像一样
It's like somebody smashed up a lot of old statues.
有雕像不见了吗
Are there any missing?
应该没有
Don't think so.
再说为什么有人会那样做
Why would anyone do that anyway?
我知道我们要保持开放的观念
I mean, I know we're meant to keep an open mind,
但我们也不能相信有生物
but are we supposed to believe in creatures
能藏在油画里
that can hide in oil paintings
而且对雕塑抱有怨恨之情吧
and have some sort of a grudge against statues?
你没事吧
You all right?
我们得走了 现在就走
We have to go - right now, this minute.
怎么了
What's wrong?
油画里的东西
The things from the paintings…
我知道他们为什么打碎了雕像
I know why they smashed the statues.
为什么 -因为他们需要地方藏起来
- Why? - Because they needed somewhere to hide.
电梯
门
博士会救我的 博士会救我的
The Doctor will save me, the Doctor will save me,
the Doctor will save me, the Doctor will save me,
博士会救我的 博士会救我的
the Doctor will save me, the Doctor will save me…
打扰一下 我需要我的呼吸器
Excuse me - I'm going to need my inhaler.
我很讨厌分到一个有缺陷的原型
I so hate it when I get one with a defect!
你有一些很可怕的记忆
Oh, you've got some perfectly horrible memories in here,
不是吗
haven't you?
那么嫉妒你漂亮的妹妹
So jealous of your pretty sister.
我不怪你 我也希望我复制的是她
I don't blame you, I wish I'd copied HER.
我也是
So do I!
看在上帝的分上
Oh, for goodness' sake… !
博士会试图给我们传递一条讯息
The Doctor will be trying to send us a message.
我们要寻找一串数字
We're looking for a string of numerals
在1550年左右的绝密级档案里
from around 1550, approximately - priority one.
我需要进入黑色档案馆
I'm going to need access to the Black Archive.
黑色档案馆
The Black Archive.
这个星球上安全等级最高的地方
Highest security rating on the planet.
全体工作人员
The entire staff have their
在每次换班后都会被抹去记忆
memories wiped at the end of every shift.
天花板上有自动记忆过滤器
Automated memory filters in the ceiling.
请求通过 -长官
- Access, please. - Ma'am.
阿特金斯 是吧
Atkins, isn't it?
是的 长官 第一天上班
Yes, ma'am. First day here.
其实有十年了
Been here ten years.
钥匙和锁 有点原始 不是吗
Lock and key - bit basic, isn't it?
这里不能都是电子安全措施
Can't afford electronic security down here -
得把博士拦在外面
got to keep the Doctor out.
整个塔都是防塔迪斯的
The whole of the Tower is TARDIS-proofed.
他不会欣赏这里的收藏品
He really wouldn't approve of the collection.
但你让我进来了
But you let me in?
你自从上次的访问后就有了最高安全权限
You have a top-level security rating from your last visit.
抱歉 你说我什么
Sorry, my what?
抱歉 我们得拍下他所有已知的同伴
Apologies. We have to screen all of his known associates -
我们不能让博士和塔迪斯的信息
we can't have information about the Doctor and the TARDIS
落入坏人之手
falling into the wrong hands.
后果将是毁灭性的
The consequences could be disastrous.
那是什么
What is that?
时间旅行
Time travel.
涡流操纵器 杰克·哈克尼斯上校
A vortex manipulator, bequeathed to the UNIT archive
去世时遗赠给UNIT档案馆的
by Captain Jack Harkness, on the occasion of his death.
当然…其中一次去世时
Well, one of them.
谁都不能知道我们有这个 盟友也不行
No-one can know we have this, not even our allies.
为什么
Why not?
想想看 让美国人拥有改写历史的能力
Think about it! Americans with the ability to rewrite history?
你也看过他们的电影
You've seen their movies.
好吧 这就是拯救博士的方法吗
OK, so this is how we're going to rescue the Doctor.
我不确定腕带的能量是否足够往返
I'm not sure there's enough power for a two-way trip.
再者 我们不知道激活代码
In any event, we don't know the activation code.
博士知道腕带在我们手上
The Doctor knows we have this,
所以一直不肯告诉我们激活代码
so he's always kept the code from us.
希望他会改变主意
Let's hope he changes his mind.
说吧
Yes.
如果你找到了
Well, if you've found it,
那就照下来发给我
photograph it and send it to my phone.
凯特 他们应该出现在这儿吗
Erm, Kate. Should they be here?
他们怎么跟来了
Why have they followed us?
他们可能只是提早处理完
Oh, they've probably just finished disposing of
那几个人类了
the humans a bit early.
人类
The humans…?
哎呀 我太入戏了 对吧
Dear me! I really do get into character, don't I?
秘密画廊已在控制之下
The Under Gallery is secured.
准备再处理一个人类
Prepare to dispose of one more human.
装置到手了
We have acquired the device.
这是激活代码对吧 -不
- Activation code, right? - No!
理论上 我可以触发分子间的
In theory, I can trigger an isolated sonic shift
隔离性音速位移
among the molecules,
这样就能瓦解这扇门
and the door should disintegrate.
我们得算出整个结构准确的谐波共振
We'd have to calculate the exact harmonic resonance
精确到亚原子级别
of the entire structure down to a sub-atomic level.
即使用音速起子也得算好多年才行
Even the sonic could take years.
不 不 音速起子要算好几百年
No, no. The sonic would take centuries.
我们不如这就开始吧
Oh, we might as well get started.
正好消磨一下"Timey-Wimey"
Help to pass the "Timey-Wimey".
你说话非要跟小孩儿一样吗
Do you have to talk like children?
成熟一点有什么好害羞的吗
What is it that makes you so ashamed of being a grown-up?
你们怎么都这样看着我 这是什么眼神
Oh, the way you both look at me. What is that?
估计没有比"畏惧"更好的形容词了
I'm trying to think of a better word than "dread".
对你来说一定记忆犹新
It must be really recent for you.
记忆犹新
Recent?
时间大战 终结之日
The Time War, the Last Day.
你毁灭一切的日子
The day you killed them all.
是我们毁灭一切的日子
The day we killed them all.
意思一样
Same thing.
对他们来说这是历史 既定的史实
It's history for them. All decided.
他们以为这个未来是真实的
They think their future is real,
他们不知道决定权还在你手上
they don't know it's still up to you.
我不想谈这件事
I don't talk about it.
你没有谈什么事
You're not talking about it.
这儿又没别人 -说下去 问他们
- There's no-one else here. - Go on. Ask them.
问他们你想知道的事
Ask them what you need to know.
你们有数过吗
Did you ever count?
数过什么
Count what?
那天在GALLIFREY上有多少孩子
How many children there were on Gallifrey that day.
我完全不知道
I have absolutely no idea.
你今年几岁了
How old are you now?
我不知道 我忘了
Ah…I don't know, I lose track.
一千二百多岁吧 除非我是在谎报年龄
Twelve hundred and something, I think, unless I'm lying.
我连自己有没有谎报年龄都忘了
I can't remember if I'm lying about my age,
可想我有多老
that's how old I am.
比我年长四百岁
400 years older than me.
在如此漫长的时光中
And in all that time,
你从没想过那天有多少个孩子吗
you've never even wondered how many there were?
你从没数过吗
You never once counted?
告诉我…
Tell me…
数了又有什么意义
what would be the point?
二十四亿七千万
2.47 billion.
你真的数过
You did count!
你居然忘了
You forgot?
四百年就能忘记吗
400 years? Is that all it takes?
我选择继续前行
I moved on.
去哪儿呢 你现在到哪里
Where?! Where can you be now
能忘掉这么沉重的事情
that you can forget something like that?
不可剧透 -不
- Spoilers. - No.
不不 这次我要知道我去哪儿
No, no, no. For once, I would like to know where I'm going.
不 你不会想知道的
No. You really wouldn't.
我不知道你们是谁
I don't know who you are… either of you.
我毫无头绪
I haven't got the faintest idea.
他们是你
They're you.
若你摧毁GALLIFREY 你就会变成他们
They're what you become if you destroy Gallifrey.
满心悔恨的人
The man who regrets…
以及遗忘过往的人
and the man who forgets.
时瞬矩即将被引爆
The Moment is coming.
我就是时瞬矩 你必须做决定
The Moment is me, you have to decide.
不行
No.
什么不行
No?
就是…不行
Just… no!
有什么好笑的
Is something funny?
我错过了什么趣事吗
Did I miss a funny thing?
抱歉 我这才意识到
Sorry. It just occurred to me.
这就是我独处时的样子
This is what I'm like when I'm alone.
这是同一个音速起子
It's the same screwdriver.
一样的软件 不同的外壳
Same software… different case.
四百年
400 years!
你说什么
I'm sorry?
就软件而言
At a software level,
它们都是同一件装置 不是吗
they're all the same device, aren't they?
一样的软件 不同的外壳
Same software, different case.
是没错 -所以说…
- Yeah. - So…?
既然要瓦解这扇门
So, it would take centuries for the screwdriver
得用音速起子算上几百年
to calculate how to disintegrate the door.
那就先扫描这扇门
Scanning the door,
将此项计算作为永久持续性子程序
implanting the calculation as a permanent subroutine
植入软件架构中
in the software architecture
然后…如果你们真的是未来的我
and… if you really are me,
即使穿着沙滩鞋或是戴着蝶形领结
with your sandshoes and your dicky bow,
那个音速起子还是我的起子
and that screwdriver is still mine…
这项计算仍在继续
that calculation is still going on.
是的 仍在计算中
Yeah. Still going.
计算完毕
Calculation complete.
一样的软件 不同的面孔
Same software. Different face.
四秒钟内飞跃四百年
Eh, 400 years in four seconds.
我们虽有分歧
We may have had our differences,
老实说 在这种情况下有够奇怪的
which is frankly odd in the circumstances,
但不得不说 伙计们
but I tell you what, boys,
我们真心绝顶聪明
we are incredibly clever!
你是怎么把门打开的
How did you that?
门没锁啊 -好吧
- It wasn't locked. - Right.
所以说他们都是你 对吧
So they're both you, then, yeah?
是的 你之前见过他们 不记得了吗
Yes. You've met them before, don't you remember?
有点印象 这西装不错
A bit. Nice suit!
谢谢
Thanks.
等等
Hang on.
你们三个同处一间牢房
Three of you in one cell,
就没有一个人想过拉开门吗
and none of you thought to try the door.
这门本该是锁上的
It should have been locked.
没错 这门为什么没锁
Yes, exactly! Why wasn't it locked?
因为我对你们会想出
Because I was fascinated to see
何等逃生大计很感兴趣
what you would do upon escaping.
我知道你们很喜欢这个世界
I understand you're rather fond of this world.
是时候让你们看看
It's time I think you saw
这世界将会发生何等巨变了
what's going to happen to it.
凯特 谢天谢地 你没死
Kate? Oh, goodness, you're not actually dead.
这真是个天大的好消息
Oh, that's tremendous news!
那些生物 他们复制了我们的形象
Those creatures, they turn themselves into copies.
他们得让原型活着 以时刻刷新图像
And they need to keep the original alive, refresh the image,
大概就是这个意思
so to speak.
他们…他们去哪儿了
Where…where did they go?
我不知道 等等 我知道
I don't know. Ooh, hang on, yes, I do.
他们去了伦敦塔
The Tower.
如果那些生物进了黑色档案馆
If those creatures have got access to the Black Archive,
我们就会失去对整个星球的控制
we may just have lost control of the planet.
扎贡人失去了他们的星球
The Zygons lost their own world.
在时间大战的第一天就被烧成灰烬
It burned in the first days of the Time War.
他们需要一个新的家园
A new home is required.
所以他们想在这里安家吗
So they want this one?
还没有 现在还太原始了
Not yet. Far too primitive.
扎贡人习惯了一定层次的生活水平
Zygons are used to a certain level of comfort.
司令
Commander…
这些生物为何会在这儿
Why are these creatures here?
因为我要他们在这儿
Because I say they should be.
该轮到你转变了
It is time you too were translated.
看好了
Observe this.
你们一定会大吃一惊的
I believe you will find it fascinating.
是他 就是那个在油画里的扎贡人
That's him! That's the Zygon in the picture now.
这不是画 这是静止魔方
It's not a picture, it's a Stasis Cube.
时间领主的技术
Time Lord art -
将瞬间冻结在时光中 里面比外面大
frozen instants in time, bigger on the inside
但是可以当作…
but could be deployed as…
假死状态 真棒
Suspended animation. Oh, that's very good.
扎贡人都钻进油画里
The Zygons all pop inside the pictures,
等上好几百年 直到这颗星球变得更有意思
wait a few centuries till the planet's a bit more interesting,
他们就跑出来了
and then out they come.
看 克拉拉
You see, Clara,
他们被保存在
they're stored in the paintings
秘密画廊的油画里 就像速食汤
in the Under Gallery, like Cup-a-Soups.
当然不考虑保质期 如果你能想象的话
Except you add time - if you can picture that.
还是别想了 忘了我说的速食汤吧
Nobody could picture that. Forget I said Cup-a-Soups.
现在这个世界可以占领了
And now the world is worth conquering.
所以扎贡人正从过去向未来发起侵略
So the Zygons are invading the future from the past.
没错
Exactly!
知道为什么我知道你是假冒的吗
And do you know why I know that you're a fake?
因为你复制得实在太糟糕了
Because you're such a bad copy.
不仅仅是那气味 那牵强的头发
It's not just the smell, or the unconvincing hair,
那凶狠的牙齿 快挤到一起的双眼
or the atrocious teeth, or the eyes just a bit too close together,
还有足以熏晕一匹马的口气
or the breath that could stun a horse -
只因为我的伊丽莎白 真正的伊丽莎白
it's because my Elizabeth, the real Elizabeth,
绝不会蠢到暴露自己的计划
would never be stupid enough to reveal her own plan.
说真的 你为什么要那样做
Honestly, why would you do that?
因为那不是我的计划
Because it's not my plan,
而且我是真正的伊丽莎白
and I am the real Elizabeth.
那么 回忆一下
OK. So…backtracking a moment,
给我前面说的话加些注释
just to lend some context to my earlier remarks…
我的复制品已经死在树林里了
My twin is dead in the forest.
我习惯了防范于未然
I am accustomed to taking precautions.
这些扎贡生物从没想过
These Zygon creatures never even considered that
活下来的是我
it was me who survived,
而不是他们的司令
rather than their own commander.
傲慢自大正是他们的特点
The arrogance that typifies their kind.
你说扎贡人
Zygons?
是男人 -你真的杀了一个扎贡人
- Men! - And you actually killed one of them?
也许我只有弱小无力的女儿身
I may have the body of a weak and feeble woman,
但当时那个扎贡人跟我是一样的
but at the time, so did the Zygon.
我王国的未来正处于危难之中
The future of my kingdom is imperilled.
博士 我能寄希望于你吗
Doctor, can I rely on your service?
没问题 我需要我的塔迪斯
Well, I'm going to need my TARDIS.
已经到手了
It has been procured already.
但首先 我的爱人 你得兑现一个承诺
But first, my love, you have a promise to keep!
我宣布 你们正式成为夫妻
I now pronounce you…man and wife.
你可以亲吻新娘了
You may kiss the bride.
将来是不是还有好多回
Is there a lot of this in the future?
这是个开始 没错
It does start to happen, yeah.
保重 我的爱人
God speed, my love.
我很快就回来
I will be right back.
好了 我们回到未来去
Right, then, back to the future.
你把这儿弄得邋遢死了
You've let this place go a bit!
他品位就这样 长大了就好多了
Ah, it's his grunge phase. He grows out of it.
不准听他们的
Don't you listen to them!
控制面板有点小故障
The desktop is glitching.
我们三个来自不同时空 它在尝试自我修正
Three of us from different time zones, it's trying to compensate.
看 这些圆圈圈
Hey, look, the round things.
我爱这些圆圈圈 -这些圆圈圈是什么
- I love the round things. - What are the round things?
不知道
No idea.
天哪 没拉反摩擦操纵杆
Oh, dear, the friction contra fibulator.
搞定 稳定了
Ha! There! Stabilised.
你重新装修过了
Oh, you've redecorated!
我不喜欢
I don't like it.
是吗
Oh? Oh, yeah.
你就没喜欢过 我们要去国家画廊
Oh, you never do! Listen, we're going to the National Gallery -
那些扎贡人就在底下
the Zygons are underneath it.
不 去UNIT总部
No, UNIT HQ,
它们跟踪我们到了黑色档案馆
they followed us there in the Black Archive.
好吧 你们都听到我说的了
OK…so you've heard of that, then.
伦敦塔
这里的设备都是非凡的
The equipment here is phenomenal.
其中很多东西的威力 人类都没有意识到
The humans don't realise what half this stuff does -
我们一天之内就能征服他们的世界
we could conquer their world in a day.
看来在选择复制品上
We were fortunate, then…
我们很幸运
in our choice of duplicate.
如果我是人类的话 我会说这是圣诞大礼
If I were human, I'd say it was Christmas.
不 别做梦了 我们没有武装 放松点
No. I'm afraid you wouldn't. We're not armed. You may relax.
我们可是全副武装的 你们该紧张才是
We are armed. You may not.
锁上门
Lock the door.
我想我们不会被打搅了
I'm afraid we can't be interrupted.
不介意我坐下吧
You don't mind if I get comfortable?
不介意我这么做吧
You don't mind if I do?
你们该意识到 这里有紧急协议保护
You'll realise there are protocols protecting this place.
奥斯古德 -在遇到外星入侵的时候
- Osgood… - In the event of alien incursion,
该房间的物品被视作极度危险品
the contents of this room are deemed so dangerous,
然后进行自毁 -五分钟后
- it will self-destruct in… - Five minutes.
在我们脚下二十英尺处有一颗核弹头
There's a nuclear warhead 20 feet beneath us.
你坐得还舒服吗
Are you sitting comfortably?
你舍得毁掉伦敦吗
You would destroy London?
为了拯救世界 我舍得
To save the world? Yes, I would.
你在虚张声势
You're bluffing.
真的吗
You really think so?
在你的记忆里 应该有一个人
Somewhere in your memory is a man called
阿利斯泰尔·戈登·莱斯布里奇-斯图尔特准将
Brigadier Alistair Gordon Lethbridge-Stewart.
我是他的女儿
I'm his daughter.
科技独尊 凯特你是这意思吗
"Science leads," Kate. Is that what you meant?
这是你父亲的意思吗
'Is this what your father meant?'
博士 -这是时空电话 凯特
- Doctor? - 'Space-Time Telegraph, Kate.'
我给你父亲的礼物 直通塔迪斯的热线电话
'A gift from me to your father, hotline straight to the TARDIS.'
我知道黑色档案馆
I know about the Black Archive
我也知道安全协议
and I know about the security protocol.
凯特 拜托了
Kate, please,
千万告诉我
please, tell me you are not
你没打算做蠢事
about to do something unbelievably stupid!
很遗憾 博士 挂掉电话
'I'm sorry, Doctor. Switch it off.'
你根本不知道以后有多遗憾
'Not as sorry as you will be.'
这个决定的后果是你绝对承受不了的
This is not a decision you will ever be able to live with.
凯特 我们正把塔迪斯开进来
Kate! We're trying to bring the TARDIS in,
为什么没法着陆
Why can't we land?
我说了挂掉
I said switch it off!
不 凯特 听我说
No, Kate, please, just listen to me…
伦敦塔 完全抵御了塔迪斯
The Tower of London - totally TARDIS-proof.
他们怎么做到的
How can they do that?
外星技术外加人类土法子
Alien technology plus human stupidity -
相信我 搞不定的
trust me, it's unbeatable.
我们不用着陆
We don't need to land.
要的 还是有一点点需要的 搞清楚状况
Yeah, we do, a tiny bit. Try and keep up.
不 不用 还有一个方法
No, we don't. We don't. There is another way.
速食汤
Cup-a-Soup!
速食汤是什么
What is Cup-a-Soup?
怎么回事
What happened?
你看了就知道
Easier to show you.
麦基洛普
McGillop.
看一下你的手机 看看你在和谁说话
Take a look at your phone and confirm who you're talking to.
这不可能 我刚刚…
But that's not possible. I was just…
还在和我说话 我明白
You were just talking to me, I know.
我是个时间旅行者 你自己琢磨去
I'm a time traveller - figure it out.
我要你把
I need you to send the
GALLIFREY之陨落那幅画转移到黑色档案馆
Gallifrey Falls painting to the Black Archive.
明白吗 -明白了 先生
- Understood? - Understood, sir.
但为什么要拿到那里去
But why would I take it there?
你一句话就能中止倒计时
One word from you would cancel the countdown.
没错
Quite so.
你的声音就是口令
It's keyed to your voice print.
而且只能是我的声音
And mine alone.
现在不只你一个了 中止计时
Not any more. Cancel the detonation!
撤回指令 -中止计时
- Countermanded! - Cancel the detonation!
撤回指令
Countermanded!
你我只有达成一致才能活命
We only have to agree to live.
可惜的是 我更想和你同归于尽
Sadly, we can only agree to die.
求你了博士 快来救救我们
Please, Doctor. Please save us.
救救我们 救救我们吧
Please save us. Please save us.
救救我们
Please save us…
消灭
Exterminate!
各位好
Hello.
我是博士
I'm the Doctor.
抱歉扔了个戴立克进来
Sorry about the Dalek.
看你们那臭显摆的劲头
Also the showing off.
凯特·莱斯布里奇-斯图尔特
Kate Lethbridge-Stewart,
你发什么神经做这种事
what in the name of sanity are you doing?
只有我亲自下令才能中止倒计时
The countdown can only be halted at my personal command.
你对此无能为力
There's nothing you can do.
除非你们俩都同意中止
Except make you both agree to halt it.
你们三个一起来我也不会同意
Not even for three of you.
你这是谋杀数百万条人命
You're aboutto murder millions of people.
为了拯救数十亿人
To save billions.
这样残酷的算数你们做过几次
How many times have you made that calculation?
只有一次
Once.
让我变成了今天这副模样
Turned me into the man I am now.
变得我自己都认不出来了
I'm not even sure who that is any more.
你自认为是彰显正义 但这只是个谎言
You tell yourself it's justified, but it's a lie.
因为我那天的所作所为错了 大错特错
Because what I did that day was wrong. Just wrong.
正因为我犯了那种错误
And because I got it wrong…
我要让你们 做正确的事
I'm going to make you… get it right.
怎么做
How?
很快你们就会叫停倒计时
Any second now, you're going to stop that countdown.
你俩一起 异口同声
Both of you. Together.
然后你们会
Then you're going to
谈判达成史上最完美的协议
negotiatethe most perfect treaty of all time.
和平共处 公平互利
Safeguards all round, fair on both sides.
而达成完美协议的关键就是
And the key to perfect negotiation…
你自己都分不清站在哪一边
Not knowing what side you're on.
因此 接下来的几小时里
So, for the next few hours…
在我们决定放过你们之前
until we decide to let you out…
这屋子里没人记得住自己究竟是人类
no-one in this room will be able to remember if they're human…
还是扎贡人
..Or Zygon.
来吧 没事啦
Whoops-a-daisy!
中止计时
Cancel the detonation!
和平降临啦
Peace in our time.
说来也有趣
It's funny, isn't it?
如果我是扎贡人 那这衣服也是扎贡人变的
If I'm a Zygon, then my clothes must be Zygon too.
那么 我万一丢了一只鞋会怎样
So, what happens if I lose a shoe or something?
你好
Hello.
你好 -我是克拉拉
- Hello. - I'm Clara.
我想你还没有见过我
We haven't really met yet.
我很期待
I look forward to it.
有什么问题吗
Is there a problem?
博士 我的…
The Doctor, my…
那位博士
my Doctor,
他经常说起那一天
he's always talking about the day he did it,
那天他灭亡了时间领主一族 以结束战争
the day he wiped out the Time Lords to stop the war.
是要做
One would.
你不会
You wouldn't.
因为你还没动手 那还是你的未来
Because you haven't done it yet. It's still in your future.
你对此坚信不疑啊
You're very sure of yourself.
他非常懊悔 我每天都能从他眼中看出来
He regrets it. I see it in his eyes every day.
他会不惜任何代价来挽回
He'd do anything to change it.
那也包括拯救这些人吗
Including saving all these people.
你觉得他的懊悔又拯救了多少个世界呢
How many worlds has his regret saved, do you think?
你看看 人类和扎贡人
Look over there, humans and Zygons
和平共处
working together in peace.
你怎么知道的呢
How did you know?
你的眼睛
Your eyes.
你年轻得多
You're so much younger.
那么 既然如此
Then, all things considered…
我该成长了
..It's time I grew up.
我该看见的都看见了
I've seen all I needed.
那一时刻已经到来
The moment has come.
我准备好了
I'm ready.
我知道
I know you are.
谁在那儿 你在和谁说话
Who's there? Who were you talking to…?
你曾希望有一个大红按钮
You wanted a big red button.
轻轻一按 所有时间领主便不再存在
One big bang, NO MORE Time Lords,
戴立克也会消失无踪
NO MORE Daleks.
你确定吗
Are you sure?
我来的时候心意已决
I was sure when I came in here.
没有别的路可走
There is no other way.
你已亲眼见过你会变成什么样子
You've seen the men you will become.
那两位啊
Those men…
都非常优秀
extraordinary.
他们曾经是你
They were you.
不是
No.
他们是博士
They were the Doctor.
你也是博士
You're the Doctor too.
我不是
No.
烈火铸英雄
Great men are forged in fire.
唯有竖子才可以不惜一切代价
It is the privilege of lesser men to light the flame…
点燃那遮天烈火
..Whatever the cost.
你还记得塔迪斯发出的那种声音吧
You know the sound the TARDIS makes?
那种呼哧呼哧的闷响
That wheezing…groaning.
无论哪里响起这个声音 希望便随之而来
That sound brings hope wherever it goes.
是的 没错 我喜欢这么想
Yes. Yes, I like to think it does.
对听到这声音的人是如此 博士
To anyone who hears it, Doctor.
对任何迷失的人
Anyone, however lost…
哪怕是你
..Even you!
我就跟你说他还没动手
I told you he hasn't done it yet.
你们几位 都走开
Go away now, all of you.
这是我自己的事
This is for me.
这一段时间应该是被锁定的
These events should be time locked
我们应该都来不了
we shouldn't even be here.
所以是谁放我们过来的
So something let us through.
这两个聪明的小子
You clever boys!
快回去
Go back.
都回到你们各自的生活去
Go back to your lives.
继续做你们的博士 而我是永远也不能了
Go and be the Doctor that I could never be.
不要辱没博士之名
Make it worthwhile.
这么多年了 我一直把你埋在记忆深处
All those years, burying you in my memory.
假装你从不曾存在
Pretending you didn't exist.
将你秘而不宣 即便是对我自己
Keeping you a secret, even from myself.
只当你不是博士
Pretending you weren't the Doctor,
而你比我们更有资格担负博士之名
when you were the Doctor more than anybody else.
在无法改变的那一天 你的的确确是博士
You were the Doctor on the day it wasn't possible to get it right.
终止
然而这次
But this time…
我们并肩作战
..you don't have to do it alone.
谢谢
Thank you.
我们今天的所作所为不是出于恐惧或憎恨
What we do today is not out of fear or hatred.
这么做是因为我们别无选择
It is done because there is no other way.
我们无力拯救的人 以他们的名义
And it is done in the name of the many lives we are failing to save.
怎么了
What?
你怎么了 出什么事了
What is it, what?
没什么
Nothing…
肯定有事 快告诉我
It's something. Tell me!
你说过你亲手杀死了你的族人 我只是
You told me you wiped out your own people. I just…
无法想象那时的你是什么样子
I never pictured you doing it,
仅此而已
that's all.
靠近看
Take a closer look.
发生什么事了
What's happening?
没什么 这是投影
Nothing,i t's a projection.
这些都是周遭的现实
It's a reality around you.
这些就是你们要亲手杀死的人
These are the people you're going to burn?
我们无能为力
There isn't anything we can do.
他说得对
He's right.
别无他法 从来都没有
There isn't another way, there never was.
要么牺牲我的族人 要么毁灭整个宇宙
Either I destroy my own people or let the universe burn.
看看你们
Look at you…
你们三个
..the three of you.
战士 英雄
The warrior. The hero.
还有你
And you.
而我又是什么呢
And what am I?
你真的忘了吗
Have you really forgotten?
是的 也许我忘了
Yes. Maybe, yes.
我们有足够多的战士
We've got enough warriors -
随便一个老笨蛋都可以当英雄
any old idiot can be hero.
那我做什么
Then what do I do?
和以前一样
What you've always done.
做你的博士
Be a doctor!
你说过你选择的名字是一种承诺
You told me the name you chose was a promise.
是什么承诺
What was the promise?
绝不残忍 绝不懦弱
Never cruel or cowardly.
永不放弃
Never give up,
永不屈服
never give in.
你当真要我们改变自己的过去
You're not actually suggesting that we change our own personal history?
我们一直在改写历史
We change history all the time.
我要做的事比这糟糕很多
I'm suggesting something far worse.
究竟是什么
What, exactly?
先生们
Gentleman,
四百年来我一直在思考这个问题
I have had 400 years to think about this.
我改变主意了
I've changed my mind.
数十亿数百亿的戴立克还没有停火
There's still a billion billion Daleks up there, attacking.
没错 说得没错
Yeah, there is, there is.
但有件事数十亿数百亿的戴立克们并不知道
But there's something those billion billion Daleks don't know.
因为如果他们发现了 很可能就派援军来了
Cos if they did, they'd probably send for reinforcements.
那是什么 他们不知道什么
What, what don't they know?
这一次 他们的敌人是三个博士
This time, there's three of us.
哦 棒极了
Oh, yes, that is good!
你真聪明
That is brilliant!
我也明白了 聪明到家了
I'm getting that too - that is brilliant!
我都想了好几百年了
I've been thinking about it for centuries!
她不光让我看到了发生过的未来
She didn't just show me any old future
她向我展示了我需要看见的未来
she showed me exactly the future I needed to see!
答对啦
Now you're getting it.
谁 -恶狼姑娘 让我亲亲你
- Eh? Who did? - Oh, Bad Wolf Girl, I could kiss you.
好吧 这事儿会发生的
Yep, that's going to happen
打断一下 你刚才说"恶狼"
Sorry, did you say, "Bad Wolf"?
我们要怎么做 什么计划
So what are we doing? What's the plan?
戴立克舰队包围了GALLIFREY
The Dalek fleets are surrounding Gallifrey,
不断地发起攻击
firing on it constantly.
天壕坚守阵地
The Sky Trench is holding,
但是如果整颗星球  突然消失
but what if the whole planet… just disappeared?
一眨眼的功夫
Tiny bit of an ask.
戴立克们就会相互开火
The Daleks would be firing on each other,
自己人打自己人
they'd destroy themselves in their own crossfire.
GALLIFREY不在了 没有了戴立克
Gallifrey would be gone, the Daleks would be destroyed,
宇宙中的其他种族会认为
and it would look to the rest of the universe
他们同归于尽了
as if they'd annihilated each other.
GALLIFREY会去哪儿呢
But where would Gallifrey be?
冰冻
Frozen!
冰冻在一个瞬间里
Frozen in an instant of time,
安全地隐藏起来
safe and hidden away.
没错
Exactly!
就像一幅油画
Like a painting.
又有一条信息
Another one!
你确定是他发来的信息
Are you sure the message is from him?
我确定 -他为什么这么做
Oh, yes! Why would he do that?
GALLIFREY不灭
那个疯子到底是什么意思
What's the mad fool talking about now?
呼叫 呼叫 GALLIFREY统帅部
Hello, hello, Gallifrey High Command,
我是博士
this is the Doctor speaking.
呼叫 我也是博士 能听见吗
Hello! Also the Doctor. Can you hear me?
我也是博士 待命
Also the Doctor, standing ready.
天哪 三个博士 噩梦啊
Dear God, three of them! All my worse nightmares at once!
将军 我们有个计划
General, we have a plan.
我们应该说明 对于这个时候
We should point out, at this moment,
这是个糟糕的计划
it is a fairly terrible plan.
一个几乎不会成功的计划
And almost certainly won't work.
我很满意"糟糕"这个词
I was happy with "Fairly terrible".
抱歉 想法外露了
Sorry, just thinking out loud.
我们将驾驶三个塔迪斯到低层大气内
We're flying our three TARDISes into your lower atmosphere.
在围绕星球的三个等距离点上排开
We're positioned at equidistant intervals round the globe.
"等距离" 大人们用的词
"Equidistant" - so grown-up!
我们准备好了
We're just about ready to do it.
你们准备好了什么
Ready to do what?
我们要冰冻GALLIFREY
We're going to freeze Gallifrey.
什么 再说一遍
I'm sorry, what?
用我们的塔迪斯
Using our TARDISes,
把GALLIFREY冷冻成时间的一瞬
we're going to freeze Gallifrey in a single moment in time.
就像那些静止魔方
You know, like those Stasis Cubes?
藏在平行口袋宇宙中的一瞬间
A single moment in time held in a parallel pocket universe.
这次我们要对整颗星球这样做
Except we're going to do it to a whole planet.
以及所有的人民
And all the people on it.
什么 即使这个计划可能成功
What? Even if that were possible,
而实际上根本不可能
which it isn't,
你们这样做的目的是什么
why would you do such a thing?
另一个方案是摧毁星球 -我经历过了
- Because the alternative is burning. - And I've seen that.
而且不想经历第二次
And I never want to see it again.
我们将会迷失在另一个宇宙中
We'd be lost in another universe…
冰冻在一个瞬间
..frozen in a single moment.
我们将会一无所有
We…we'd have nothing.
你们有希望
You would have hope.
那正是你们此时此刻没有的
And right now, that is exactly what you don't have.
那是不可能的 光是计算就要花费
It's delusional. The calculations alone would take..
好几百年
hundreds of years.
是的 几百年又几百年 -不过别担心
- Oh, hundreds and hundreds. - But don't worry
我很早很早以前就开始了
I started a very long time ago!
呼叫GALLIFREY军事议会 我是博士
Calling the War Council of Gallifrey, this is the Doctor.
可以说 我这一生一直在这么做
You might say, I've been doing this all my lives!
祝你好运 -待命
- 'Good luck!' - 'Stand by.'
准备好了吗 -速率计算
- 'Ready?' - 'Commencing calculations.'
马上到达
Soon be there.
穿越分离宇宙的边界
Across the boundaries that divide one universe from another.
只要锁定坐标
Just got to lock on to his coordinates.
我的下一招…
And for my next trick… !
还要不要我活下去 十二个都来了
I didn't know when I was well off! All 12 of them!
不 阁下
No, sir…
是十三个
..All 13!
阁下 戴立克察觉到什么了
Sir! The Daleks know that something is happening.
他们的火力越来越强
They're increasing their fire power.
做吧 博士
Do it, Doctor.
快做吧
Just do it.
做吧
'Do it!'
好
Ok.
先生们 我们准备好了
'Gentleman…we're ready.'
Geronimo…!
出发
Allons-y!
饶了我吧
Oh, for God's sake!
GALLIFREY不灭
Gallifrey stands!
我不指望能知道我们有没有成功
I don't suppose we'll ever know if we actually succeeded.
最坏的情况就是
But at worst,
我们失败了 但事情是对的
we failed doing the right thing,
而不是成功地做了一件错事
as opposed to succeeding in doing the wrong.
你们可是关键人物
Life and soul, you are!
这幅画到底叫什么呢
What is it actually called?
存在争论
Well, there's some debate.
NO MORE
Either NO MORE
或者GALLIFREY之陨落
or Gallifrey Falls.
都挺泄气的
Not very encouraging.
这画怎么来这儿的
How did it get here?
不知道
No idea.
总有些我们不知道的事情 对吧
There's always something we don't know, isn't there?
没有可就惨了
One should certainly hope so.
先生们
Well, gentlemen…
我很荣幸
it has been an honour…
有这个机会
and a privilege.
一样一样 -博士
- Likewise. - Doctor.
如果我能有你一半的聪明才智
And if I grow to be half the man that you are,
克拉拉·奥斯瓦德 我会很高兴的
Clara Oswald, I shall be happy indeed.
这才对嘛 志向远大
That's right - aim high!
我不会记得这些 是吧
I won't remember this, will I?
时间之河各有其流向
The time streams are out of sync.
你无法记住 是的
You can't retain it, no.
那我就记不住我曾拼力拯救GALLIFREY
So I won't remember that I tried to save Gallifrey,
只会认为我炸了它
rather than burn it.
带着悔恨活下去了
I'll have to live with that.
不过此时
But for now,
此刻
for this moment…
我又一次成为博士
..I am the Doctor again.
谢谢你们
Thank you.
哪一个是我的
Which one is mine?!
是了
Oh, yes…
这就对了 这才说得通
Course, suppose it makes sense…
终于到来了
Wearing a bit thin.
希望这次耳朵别太招风
I hope the ears are bit less conspicuous this time.
我也不会记得 所以你不妨告诉我吧
I won't remember either, so you might as well tell me.
告诉你什么
Tell you what?
你不想提到的 我们最终要去的地方
Where it is we're going that you don't want to talk about.
我看到了Trenzalore
I saw Trenzalore…
我们的埋骨之地
where we're buried.
数百万人战死 我们也在其中
We die in battle among millions.
不该是那样
That's not how it's supposed to be.
这就是故事的完结 我们无能为力
That's how the story ends - nothing we can do about it.
Trenzalore就是你要去的地方
Trenzalore is where you're going.
别说得这么绝对
Oh, never say nothing.
不过呢
Anyway…
很高兴知道我的未来安然无恙
good to know my future is in safe hands.
盯紧一点 克拉拉
Keep a tight hold on it, Clara.
盯着呢
Mm! On it!
Trenzalore
我们需要一个新的终点 因为
We need a new destination, because…
我不想走
..I don't want to go.
他总这么说
He always says that.
你想独自看一会儿画吗
Need a moment alone with your painting?
你怎么知道 -悲伤的大眼睛说的
- How did you know? - Those big, sad eyes.
我从来都知道
I always know.
差点忘了 有一位老人找你
Oh, by the way, there was an old man looking for you.
可能是馆长
I think it was the curator.
我可以当馆长
I could be a curator.
当馆长我可厉害了
I'd be great at curating.
我会成为伟大的馆长
I'd be…the great curator.
我可以退休 然后干这个
I could retire and do that.
我可以退休 然后在这里当馆长
I could retire and be the curator of this place.
我觉得你真的会这样
You know, I really think you might.
我忘不了这张脸
I never forget a face.
我知道你不会忘 在往后的岁月中
I know you don't, and in years to come,
你会发现自己不断地重温
you might find yourself revisiting a few
一些老掉牙的故人旧事
but just…the old favourites, eh?
你对这幅画很好奇
You were curious about this painting, I think.
我是因特别的机缘才得到它的
I acquired it in remarkable circumstances.
你怎么看它的名字
What do you make of the title?
哪个名字 有两个呢
Which title? There's two.
NO MORE…
还是GALLIFREY之陨落
..Or Gallifrey Falls?
其实大家都想错了
Oh, you see, that's where everybody's wrong.
就是一个名字
It's all one title.
GALLIFREY永不陨落
Gallifrey Falls No More.
你觉得那是什么意思
Now, what would you think that means, eh?
GALLIFREY没有陨落
That Gallifrey didn't fall.
成功了 它还存在
It worked. It's still out there.
我只是个卑微的馆长 我哪里知道呢
I'm only a humble curator - I'm sure I wouldn't know.
它在哪里 -到底在哪里呢
- Then where is it? - Where is it indeed?
是 -不见了 或许吧
- Yes. - Lost - shh! - perhaps.
万事万物都有失落之时
Things do get lost, you know.
请恕我失陪
Now you must excuse me.
你还有很多事情
you have a lot to do.
是吗 我现在是不是就该去呢
Do I? Mm. Is that what I'm supposed to do now?
去寻找GALLIFREY
Go looking for Gallifrey?
这完全看你 你的选择
Oh, it's entirely up to you. Your choice.
我只能说我会怎么做
I can only tell you what I would do,
如果我是你
if I were you…
噢 如果我是你
Oh… ! If I were you…
也许我以前就是你呢
Perhaps I WAS you, of course.
也许
Or perhaps…
你就是我
you are me.
是啊 -恭喜
- Yeah! - Congratulations.
非常感谢
Thank you very much.
也许 无论哪样都没关系
Or perhaps it doesn't matter either way.
谁知道呢
Who knows?
谁知道
Who…Noses?
克拉拉有时问我是否做梦
Clara sometimes asks me if I dream.
我当然做梦 我告诉她
"Course I dream," I tell her.
人人都会做梦
"Everybody dreams.
你都梦些什么 她问
"But what do you dream about?" She'll ask.
跟其他人的梦差不多 我告诉她
"The same thing everybody dreams about," I tell her.
我梦见将要去的地方
"I dream about where I'm going."
她听了就笑
She always laughs at that.
但你没有什么去处 只是流浪
"But you're not going anywhere - you're just wandering about."
并非如此 不再是这样了
That's not true. Not any more.
我有新的去处了
I have a new destination.
我的旅程跟你们的一样 跟大家的一样
My journey is the same as yours, the same as anyone's.
花了我很多年 很多辈子
It's taken me so many years, so many lifetimes,
终于我知道了要去哪里
but at last I know where I'm going,
我永远在前往的地方
where I've always been going.
回家 绕了好大一圈呢
'Home…the long way round.'